Guide to the Norman Finkelstein Collection BCMS.0067
Brooklyn Collection
Norman Finkelstein Collection
1939-2017
1980-2005
Brooklyn Collection
Finkelstein, Norman, 1954-
BCMS.0067
19 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons, 1 oversize folder in flat file
Materials documenting the career of activist, author and educator Norman Finkelstein. His areas of study include the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, Zionism and Holocaust exploitation.
Biographical Note
Norman Finkelstein was born in Brooklyn in 1953 to Holocaust survivors Mary and Zacharias Finkelstein. He attended James Madison High School followed by Binghamton College, where he graduated in 1974 with a degree in History. Finkelstein enrolled at Princeton University where he earned a Master's degree in political science and a PhD in political studies in 1988. He also studied at the École Pratique des Hautes Études in Paris.
After graduation Finkelstein held teaching positions at various universities including New York University, Brooklyn College and Hunter College. His dissertation, The Jewish Question to the Jewish State: An Essay on the Theory of Zionism became the foundation for his first book, Image and Reality of the Israel-Palestine Conflict (Verso, 1995), a critical analysis of Joan Peters' From Time Immemorial: The Origins of the Arab-Jewish Conflict over Palestine (Harpercollins, 1984). The book earned both criticism and support from the academic community, with public figures such as Noam Chomsky coming to Finkelstein's defense. Image and Reality was followed by The Rise and Fall of Palestine: A personal account of the intifada years (University of Minnesota, 1996) and A Nation on Trial: The Goldhagen thesis and historical truth (with Ruth Bettina Birn) (Henry Holt, 1998).
In 2000 Finkelstein released his most publicized book to date, The Holocaust Industry: Reflections on the Exploitation of Jewish Suffering (Verso, 2000). Finkelstein argued that the memory of the Holocaust was being exploited by the American Jewish community for financial gain while allowing Israel to commit human rights abuses unchecked. While the book received some positive reviews it also brought accusations of holocaust denial and the possibility of exploitation for anti-Semitic purposes.
In 2001 Finkelstein accepted a teaching position at DePaul University's College of Liberal Arts and Social Sciences. His continued advocacy for the people of Palestine and criticism of Israeli human rights policies made him a prominent voice in the ongoing conflict. In 2003 Harvard professor Alan Dershowitz released The Case for Israel (John Wiley & Sons), prompting a rebuttal from Finkelstein that played out in the press and resulted in Finkelstein's next book, Beyond Chutzpah: On the misuse of anti-Semitism and the abuse of history (University of California Press, 2005). Finkelstein accused Dershowitz of plagiarizing portions of Peters' From Time Immemorial and even questioning the book's authorship, causing Dershowitz to threaten legal action against the publisher. Beyond Chutzpah was released without the word "plagiarism" and did not include accusations about The Case for Israel's authorship.
Finkelstein became eligible for tenure at DePaul University in 2007. In September of that year Dershowitz began contacting various university employees and alumni in an effort to block Finkelstein's tenure bid. Although he was initially approved, a minority report was filed by several faculty members and Finkelstein was ultimately denied. Despite ongoing support from students and colleagues he was placed on leave and submitted his resignation in September 2007. DePaul insisted Dershowitz's interference didn't influence the decision.
After leaving DePaul Finkelstein returned to Brooklyn, where he continues to publish and speak on Middle East relations. His books have been translated into more than 50 foreign editions. Finkelstein's life and career was the subject of a 2009 award winning documentary, American Radical: The Trials of Norman Finkelstein, directed by David Ridgen and Nicolas Rossier. He was also the subject of the 2017 Off-Broadway production, If I Forget, written by Steven Levenson.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials documenting the education and career of Norman Finkelstein. The bulk of the collection includes materials from his first five books: Image and Reality of the Israel-Palestine Conflict (Verso, 1995), The Rise and Fall of Palestine: A personal account of the intifada years (University of Minnesota, 1996), A Nation on Trial: The Goldhagen thesis and historical truth (with Ruth Bettina Birn) (Henry Holt, 1998), The Holocaust Industry: Reflections on the exploitation of Jewish suffering (Verso, 2000) and Beyond Chutzpah: On the misuse of anti-Semitism and the abuse of history (University of California Press, 2005). Research materials for each book include court documents, essays, clippings and reports. Book items also include chapter drafts, reviews and press for both American and international editions. Some contain administrative paperwork, contracts and royalty statements.
Items from Finkelstein's education span from elementary school to his years at Princeton, with the bulk consisting of materials for his dissertation, The Jewish Question to the Jewish State: An Essay on the Theory of Zionism. Dissertation items include the final manuscript, drafts, revisions and handwritten notecards. Materials from his undergraduate work at Binghamton University consist of papers and exams; his elementary, middle and high school items include certificates and report cards.
Notebooks kept for personal use contain handwritten notes on various books including The Wealth of Nations, Leviathan and The Marx-Engels Reader. Materials concerning speaking tours and conferences are also inlcuded.
Related Materials
Ehrenreich, Jake. A Jew grows in Brooklyn: the curious reflections of a first-generation American. Health Communications, 2010.
Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York. Demographic Study Committee. The Jewish population of the New York area, 1900-1975.
Hecht, Eli. Crossing the Williamsburg Bridge: memories of an American youngster growing up with Chassidic survivors of the holocaust. Xlibris, 2004.
Jewish Communal Survey of Greater New York. Executive Committee. Jewish communal survey of Greater New York. 1929.
Additional Related Materials Held by the Brooklyn Public Library:
Finkelstein, Norman. Gaza: an inquest into its martyrdom. University of California Press, 2018.
Finkelstein, Norman. The Holocaust industry: reflections on the exploitation of Jewish suffering (2nd edition). Verso, 2003.
Finkelstein, Norman. Image and reality of the Israel-Palestine conflict (2nd edition). Verso, 2003.
Finkelstein, Norman. A Nation on Trial: The Goldhagen thesis and historical truth. H. Holt, 1998.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Advance notice required. The collection can be accessed by appointment only, with supervised use. Patron must present Identification at time of visit.
Provenance
This collection was donated by Norman Finkelstein in 2018.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Books is arranged in six subseries, chronologically by book title. Items in each subseries are loosely arranged by topic.
Series II: Lectures, Conferences and Essays is arranged by topic.
Series III: Notebooks is not arranged.
Series IV: Education is arranged by school. Items for each school are arranged by topic. Series V: Correspondence is arranged by topic.
Collection items foldered by Norman Finkelstein prior to donation have been left in original order. Folders created by the archivist have been marked with an asterisk in the collection inventory.
Arab-Israeli conflict; Holocaust; Israel; Jews--Politics and government; Jews--United States; Middle East--Politics and government; Palestine; Zionism; Dershowitz, Alan, 1938-; Peters, Joan, 1936-2015
- Series I: Books
  - Subseries I: Image and Reality
    - Research, Introduction, English Edition, 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Research, Benny Morris Chapter, 1956-1959, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - Research, Shapira Chapter, 1939, 1955-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Research and Notes, 1967/1973 Chapter (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - Research, pre-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Reviews, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - *Talks and Appearances, Finkelstein and Peters, 1961, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Israeli Publications, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Finkelstein's Letters to the Editor, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Finkelstein's Letters to the Editor, British Publications, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Research and Notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Protocalls of Joan Peters, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Disinformation and the Palestine Question, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Personal Correspondence, Essays, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Time Immemorial Reviews, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Time Immemorial, British Reviews, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Royalties, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Contract, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - *Clippings, 1984-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Subseries II: Rise and Fall
    - Press, Administrative, Correspondence, 1996-1997, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - Postscript, Royalties for German Edition, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Administrative and Promotions, German Edition, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Saddam Hussein (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cherokee (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - *Clippings, circa 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Subseries III: A Nation on Trial
    - Research, 1946-1997 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Reviews, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Hitler's Willing Executioners, Reviews, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Hitler's Willing Executioners, German Reviews, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - New Left Review, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Unwilling Germans? Manuscript, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - *Royalties, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - *Contract, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - *Henry Holt and Co. Publicity, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - *Rod Driver Campaign, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Book Jacket, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - *Talks and Public Appearances, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - NormanFinkelstein.com, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - *Clippings, 1997-2006 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Subseries IV: Holocaust Industry
    - Research, Appendix, Second Edition, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Research, Second Post Script, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
    - Research, Second Post Script, Additions, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Research, Forward and Postscript, 1996, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Writing and Research, Preface to German Edition, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Manuscript, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript, Forward to First Paperback Edition/Postscript to Second Edition, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Research, Postscript, Additions, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Research, Postscript, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Research, Introduction and Chapter 2, 1951, 1985-2000 (Box 5, Folder 5-9)
    - Hollow-caust, circa 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Draft, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Research and Manuscript, Forward to German Edition/Revised Afterward to Polish Edition, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Research and Manuscript, Forward to German Edition/Revised Afterward to Polish Edition, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Research, Poland/Austria/Eastern Europe Edition, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Swiss Banks, 1951, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 3-6)
    - Switzerland and Refugees in the Nazi Era, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Switzerland and Global Transactions in the Second World War, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Dutch Insurance Claims, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Insurance Claims, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
    - Research and Correspondence, International Commission on Holocaust Era Insurance Claims, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Association of Dutch Insurers, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - German Slave Labor, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - German Reparations and the Jewish World, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Holocaust Victim Asset Litigation, Special Master's Proposal, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
    - Switzerland, National Socialism and the Second World War, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - The European Legacy, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Dormant Accounts of Victims of Nazi Persecution in Swiss Banks, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Plunder and Restitution, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Research, General, 2000-2003 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Knesset Report on Israeli Banks, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - SOJA Business, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - PCHA Report, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Jean-Christian, Lambelet Article, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Von Gunner Heinsohn Article, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Bronner Family and Sam Pisar, 1996-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Raul Hilberg Interview, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - *Peter Novik, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Research and Response, Jan T. Gross, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Holocaust Victim Assets Litigation Vol I, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Holocaust Victim Assets Litigation, Vol II, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Holocaust Victim Assets Litigation, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Cobell v. Babbitt, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Cobell v. Babbitt, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Cobell v. Babbit/Summers/Gover, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Cobell v. Norton Appeal, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Cobell v. Babbit/Rubin/Gover, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Babbitt v. Norton, 2002-2003 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Polish Cases, 1999-2002 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Congressional Report, Mismanagement of the Indian Trust Fund, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Application of Burt Neuborne, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Bound Clippings, Holocaust Controversies, 1979-2000 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Bound Clippings, Holocaust "Blackmail" "Extortion", 1997-2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Bound Clippings, Holocaust Industry, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bound Clippings, Media References, 1980-2000 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - German Press, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Lecture Tour, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Box 5)
    - Public Relations Trip to Germany, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Fordham Conference, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Contact Information (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Book Ads, 2000-2004 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - La Fabrique, 2001-2004 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Reviews and Responses, 2000-2002 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Royalties Statements and Contracts, 1999-2003 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - *Clippings, 2000-2007 (Box 9, Folder 13-16)
    - *Nahos Newsletter, 2004-2007 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Subseries V: Beyond Chutzpah
    - Research, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - *Research, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - *Research, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - *Research, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - *Research, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - *Research, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - *Research, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - *Research, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - *Research, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - *Research, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
    - *Research, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
    - *Research, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - *Research, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    - Al-Haq, 1988-1990 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Columbia Coda, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Israeli Supreme Court, 1989, 1993-2004 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - New Anti-Semitism (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
    - New Anti-Semitism (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Atta Testimony, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Critique of Practical Reason (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Legal Correspondence, 2004-2007 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Dershowitz Writing, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Dershowitz Libel, 2013 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Royalties, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Research and Correspondence, One Day in September (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Clippings and Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
    - Comments on Revisions, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Criticism of Finkelstein, 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, Dershowitz, 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - The University of California Press Contract, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Pitch, Evaluations, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Research, Appendix (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Research, Complete Appendix, 1937, 1981-2004 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Research, Complete Appendix, 1979, 2001-2004 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - German Introduction, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Research, New Introduction Additions, 2005-2006 (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
    - Original Manuscript, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Research, Plagiarism Chapter, 2000-2004 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Images, Plagiarism Chapter (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Research, Human Rights Chapter, 1971-2004 (Box 13, Folder 8-12)
    - Research, Human Rights Chapter, 1993-2005 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Clippings with Index, 1997, 2007 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 2005-2007 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
    - Back to Basics, New Intro for German Edition, 2002 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Subseries VI: Knowing Too Much
    - Oren, Michael. Six Days of War, Research and Reviews, 1968-2003 (Box 19, Folder 15-16)
- Series II: Lectures, Conferences and Essays
  - *Lectures, circa 1995-2001 (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
  - Macalester College Lecture, First the Carrot, 1999-2002 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
  - Clippings, Lectures, circa 2008 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - International Conference on Alternative Development Strategies and the Future of Asia, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - World Peace Foundation Conference, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Max Planck Institute Conference, 2017 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Essay and Reviews, Professor Said and Palestine, circa 1996 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Whither the Peace Process, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, American Radical, 2010 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - *Flyers and Photographs, 1982-1989 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - *Clippings, General, 1976-2007 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Israel and Iraq- A Double Standard, Follow Up, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - *Lecture Posters, 1989 (Cabinet Morgue Flat File 1, Drawer 11)
- Series III: Notebooks
  - *Notebooks (Box 15, Folder 1-8)
  - Address Book (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Education
  - Dissertation Notecards (Box 16)
  - Dissertation Notecards (Box 17)
  - Dissertation, Manuscript, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Dissertation, Draft, Handwritten, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation, Draft, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
  - Dissertation, Second Draft, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation, Notebooks, circa 1986 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation, Wolin and Falk Revisions, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation, Clippings, 1975-1986 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation, Zionism, Race, Nationalism and the Nation State, circa 1985 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - *Dissertation, Publishing and Microfilming Information, 1984-1986 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Dissertation, Approval, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Dissertation, Correspondence, Noam Chomsky, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Princeton, Papers, 1976-1978 (Box 18, Folder 13-14)
  - Harpur College (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Columbia College Application, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Binghamton, Papers, 1970-1973 (Box 18, Folder 17-18)
  - Binghamton, Papers and Exams, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Binghamton, Mao Tse-Tung's Revolutionary Line in Higher Education, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Binghamton, Phi Beta Kappa, circa 1973 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - James Madison High School, 1967-1971 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Roy Mann Junior High School, 1965-1967 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - P.S. 236, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 24)
- Series V: Correspondence
  - Image and Reality, 1980-1986 (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - A Nation on Trial, 1997-1999 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Holocaust Industry, 1998-2004 (Box 19, Folder 5-7)
  - General, 1971-2005 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Washington Post / Georgetown University, 1989-2002 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Mary Finkelstein's Holocaust Compensation Claim, 1948-1995 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Hudson Guild, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Brooklyn College, 1988-1992 (Box 19, Folder 12)